<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Rinconete y Cortadillo: Digital Edition</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>created by</resp>
					<name>Rebecca Beattie</name>				
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>University of Bologna</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Seville, Spain</pubPlace>
				<date>2022</date>
				<availability>
					<p>Digital Edition based on a print, critical edition, edited by Harry Sieber and published by Cátedra. This digital edition respects the rights outlined in this source, quoted here.</p>
					<p xml:lang="es">Reservados todos los derechos. El contenido de esta obra está protegido por la Ley, que establece penas de prisión y/o multas, además de las correspondientes indemnizaciones por daños y perjuicios, para quienes reprodujeren, plagiaren, distribuyeren o comunicaren públicamente, en todo o en parte, una obra literaria, artística o científica, o su transformación, interpretación o ejecución artística fijada en cualquier tipo de soporte o comunicada a través de cualquier medio, sin la preceptiva autorización</p>
					<p>The English text is freely and openly available from <ref target="http://www.online-literature.com/cervantes/exemplary-novels/2/">http://www.online-literature.com/cervantes/exemplary-novels/2/</ref></p>
					<p>Information regarding use of content from the Biblioteca Nacional de Espana can be found at <ref target="http://www.bne.es/es/Catalogos/BibliotecaDigitalHispanica/Pie/AvisoLegal/">http://www.bne.es/es/Catalogos/BibliotecaDigitalHispanica/Pie/AvisoLegal/</ref></p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl>
					<author>	
						<name>
							<surname>de Cervantes</surname>
							<forename>Miguel</forename>
						</name>
					</author>
					<editor>
						<name>
							<surname>de Robles</surname>
							<forename>Francisco</forename>
						</name>
					</editor>
					<title xml:lang="es">Novelas ejemplares</title>
					<publisher>Juan de la Cuesta</publisher>
					<pubPlace>Madrid, Spain</pubPlace>
					<date>1613</date>
				</bibl>
				<bibl>
					<author>	
						<name>
							<surname>de Cervantes</surname>
							<forename>Miguel</forename>
						</name>
					</author>
					<editor>
						<name>
							<surname>Sieber</surname>
							<forename>Harry</forename>
						</name>
					</editor>
					<title xml:lang="es">Novelas ejemplares I</title>
					<publisher>Ediciones Cátedra</publisher>
					<pubPlace>Madrid, Spain</pubPlace>
					<date>2009</date>
				</bibl>
				<bibl>
					<author>	
						<name>
							<surname>de Cervantes</surname>
							<forename>Miguel</forename>
						</name>
					</author>
					<editor>
						<name>
							<surname>Kelly</surname>
							<forename>Walter</forename>
						</name>
					</editor>
					<title xml:lang="es">Rinconete and Cortadillo. Or, Peter of the Corner and the Little Cutter</title>
					<publisher>The Literature Network</publisher>
					<date>1881</date>
				</bibl>	
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<normalization>
					<p>In the 1613 edition of the text, words, or partial words, at the end of a page are repeated, or partially repeated, at the start of the next page. The transription to go alongside the digitisation of the 1613 version standardises this practice by including the whole of the final word at the end of a page, and again at the start of the next page.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	
	<facsimile>
		<graphic url="FacsimileImages/66a.jpg"/>
	</facsimile>
	
	<text>
		<body>
			<div xml:lang="es">
				<p>y ceñida por los pechos, traía el uno una camisa de color de camuza, encerrada y recogida toda en una manga; el otro venía escueto y sin alforjas, puesto que en el seno se le parecía un gran bulto, que, a lo que después pareció, era un cuello de los que llaman valonas, almidonado con grasa, y tan deshilado de roto, que todo parecia hilachas. Venían en él envueltos y guardados unos naipes de figura ovada, porque de ejercitarlos se les habían gastado las puntas, y porque durasen más se las cercenaron y los dejaron de aquel talle. Estaban los dos quemados del sol, las uñas caireladas, y las manos no muy limpias; el uno tenía una media espada, y el otro, un cuchillo de cachas amarillas, que los suelen llamar vaqueros.</p>

				<p>Saliéronse los dos a sestear en un portal o cobertizo que delante de la venta se hace, y sentándose frontero el uno del otro, el que parecía de mas edad dijo al mas pequeño:</p>

				<p><q>--¿De qué tierra es vuesa merced, señor gentilhombre, y para adónde bueno camina?</q></p>

				<p><q>--Mi tierra, señor caballero - respondió el preguntado -, no la sé, ni para dónde camino, tampoco.</q></p>

				<p><q>--Pues en verdad - dijo el mayor - que no parece vuesa merced del cielo, y que éste no es lugar para hacer su asiento en él: que por fuerza se ha de pasar adelante.</q></p>

				<p><q>--Así es - respondió el mediano -; pero yo he dicho verdad en lo que he dicho; porque mi tierra no es mía, pues no tengo en ella más que un padre que no me tiene por hijo y una madrastra que me trata como alnado; el camino que llevo es a la ventura, y allí le daría fin donde hallase quien me diese lo necesario para pasar esta miserable vida.</q></p>

				<p><q>--Y ¿sabe vuesa merced algun oficio? - preguntó el grande.</q></p>

				<p>Y el menor respondió:</p>

				<p><q>--No sé otro sino que corro como una liebre, y salto como un gamo, y corto de tijera muy delicadamente.</q></p>

				<p><q>--Todo eso es muy bueno, útil y provechoso - dijo el grande -, porque habrá sacristan que le dé a vuesa merced la ofrenda de Todos Santos por que para el Juéves Santo le corte florones de papel para el monumento.</q></p>

				<p><q>--No es mi corte desa manera - respondió el menor -, sino que</q></p>
			</div>
			
			<div xml:lang="en">
				<p>crossing his breast like a scarf, one of them carried a shirt, the colour of chamois leather; the body of this garment was rolled up and thrust into one of its sleeves: the other, though travelling without incumbrance, bore on his chest what seemed a large pack, but which proved, on closer inspection, to be the remains of a starched ruff, now stiffened with grease instead of starch, and so worn and frayed that it looked like a bundle of hemp.</p>

				<p>Within this collar, wrapped up and carefully treasured, was a pack of cards, excessively dirty, and reduced to an oval form by repeated paring of their dilapidated corners. The lads were both much burned by the sun, their hands were anything but clean, and their long nails were edged with black; one had a dudgeon-dagger by his side; the other a knife with a yellow handle.</p>

				<p>These gentlemen had selected for their siesta the porch or penthouse commonly found before a Venta; and, finding themselves opposite each other, he who appeared to be the elder said to the younger, <q>"Of what country is your worship, noble Sir, and by what road do you propose to travel?"</q> <q>"What is my country, Señor Cavalier," returned the other, "I know not; nor yet which way my road lies."</q></p>

				<p><q>"Your worship, however, does not appear to have come from heaven," rejoined the elder, "and as this is not a place wherein a man can take up his abode for good, you must, of necessity, be going further."</q> <q>"That is true," replied the younger; "I have, nevertheless, told you only the veritable fact; for as to my country, it is mine no more, since all that belongs to me there is a father who does not consider me his child, and a step-mother who treats me like a son-in-law. With regard to my road, it is that which chance places before me, and it will end wherever I may find some one who will give me the wherewithal to sustain this miserable life of mine."</q></p>

				<p><q>"Is your worship acquainted with any craft?" inquired the first speaker.</q> <q>"With none," returned the other, "except that I can run like a hare, leap like a goat, and handle a pair of scissors with great dexterity."</q></p>

				<p><q>"These things are all very good, useful, and profitable," rejoined the elder. "You will readily find the Sacristan of some church who will give your worship the offering-bread of All Saints' Day, for cutting him his paper flowers to decorate the Monument on Holy Thursday."</q></p>

				<p><q>"But that is not my manner of cutting," replied the younger.</q></p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>



