<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Rinconete y Cortadillo: Digital Edition</title>
				<author>Miguel de Cervantes</author>
				<editor>Harry Sieber</editor>
				<editor>Rebecca Beattie</editor>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>University of Bologna</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Seville, Spain</pubPlace>
				<date>2022</date>
				<availability>
					<p>Digital Edition based on a print, critical edition, edited by Harry Sieber and published by Cátedra. This digital edition respects the rights outlined in this source. The English text is freely and openly available from <ref target="http://www.online-literature.com/cervantes/exemplary-novels/2/">http://www.online-literature.com/cervantes/exemplary-novels/2/</ref></p>
					<p xml:lang="es">Reservados todos los derechos. El contenido de esta obra está protegido por la Ley, que establece penas de prisión y/o multas, además de las correspondientes indemnizaciones por daños y perjuicios, para quienes reprodujeren, plagiaren, distribuyeren o comunicaren públicamente, en todo o en parte, una obra literaria, artística o científica, o su transformación, interpretación o ejecución artística fijada en cualquier tipo de soporte o comunicada a través de cualquier medio, sin la preceptiva autorización</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl>
					<author>	
						<name>
							<surname>de Cervantes</surname>
							<forename>Miguel</forename>
						</name>
					</author>
					<editor>
						<name>
							<surname>Sieber</surname>
							<forename>Harry</forename>
						</name>
					</editor>
					<title xml:lang="es">Novelas ejemplares</title>
					<publisher>Ediciones Cátedra</publisher>
					<pubPlace>Madrid, Spain</pubPlace>
					<date>2009</date>
				</bibl>	
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<normalization>
					<p>In the 1613 edition of the text, words, or partial words, at the end of a page are repeated, or partially repeated, at the start of the next page. The transription to go alongside the digitisation of the 1613 version standardises this practice by including the whole of the final word at the end of a page, and again at the start of the next page.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	
	<facsimile>
		<graphic url="FacsimileImages/72.jpg"/>
	</facsimile>
	
	<text>
		<body>
		<div xml:lang="es">
			<p><q>envesados y de sesenta y dos en gurapas.</q></p>

			<p><q>--En verdad, señor - dijo Rincón -, que así entendemos esos nombres como volar.</q></p>

			<p><q>--Comencemos a andar, que yo los iré declarando por el camino - respondió el mozo -, con otros algunos que así les conviene saberlos como el pan de la boca.</q></p>

			<p>Y así, les fue diciendo y declarando otros nombres de los que ellos llaman germanescos o de la germanía, en el discurso de su plática, que no fue corta, porque el camino era largo. En el cual dijo Rincón a su guía:</p>

			<p><q>--¿Es vuesa merced, por ventura, ladrón?</q></p>

			<p><q>--Sí - respondió él -, para servir a Dios y a las buenas gentes, aunque no de los muy cursados; que todavía estoy en el año del noviciado.</q></p>

			<p>A lo cual respondió Cortado:</p>

			<p><q>--Cosa nueva es para mí que haya ladrones en el mundo para servir a Dios y a la buena gente.</q></p>

			<p>A lo cual respondió el mozo:</p>

			<p><q>--Señor, yo no me meto en tologías; lo que sé es que cada uno en su oficio puede alabar a Dios, y más con la órden que tiene dada Monipodio a todos sus ahijados.</q></p>

			<p><q>--Sin duda - dijo Rincón - debe de ser buena y santa, pues hace que los ladrones sirvan a Dios.</q></p>

			<p><q>--Es tan santa y buena - replicó el mozo -, que no sé yo si se podrá mejorar en nuestro arte. Él tiene ordenado que de lo que hurtáremos demos alguna cosa o limosna para el aceite de la lámpara de una imágen muy devota que está en esta ciudad, y en verdad que hemos visto grandes cosas por esta buena obra; porque los días pasados dieron tres ansias a un cuatrero que había murciado dos roznos, y con estar flaco y cuartanario, así los sufrió sin cantar como si fueran nada. Y esto atribuimos los del arte a su buena devoción, porque sus fuerzas no eran bastantes para sufrir el primer desconcierto del verdugo. Y porque sé que me han de preguntar algunos vocablos de los que he dicho, quiero curarme en salud y decírselo antes que me lo pregunten. Sepan voacedes que cuatrero es ladron de bestias; ansia es el tormento;</q></p>
		</div>
			
		<div xml:lang="en">
			<p><q>lost leather; and but sixty-two have been lagged."</q></p>

			<p><q>"Truly, Sir," rejoined Rincon, "all this is Hebrew to us; we know no more about it than we do of flying."</q></p>

			<p><q>"Let us be jogging, then," replied the new-comer, "and on the way I will explain to you these and other things, which it is requisite you should know as pat as bread to mouth;" </q>and, accordingly, he explained to them a whole vocabulary of that thieves' Latin which they call Germanesco, or Gerigonza, and which their guide used in the course of his lecture,--by no means a short one, for the distance they had to traverse was of considerable length.</p>

			<p>On the road, Rincon said to his new acquaintance, <q>"Does your worship happen to be a Thief?"</q></p>

			<p><q>"Yes," replied the lad, "I have that honour, for the service of God and of all good people; but I cannot boast of being among the most distinguished, since I am as yet but in the year of my novitiate."</q></p>

			<p><q>"It is news to me," remarked Cortado, "that there are thieves for the service of God and of good people."</q></p>

			<p><q>"Señor," the other replied, "I don't meddle with theology; but this I know, that every one may serve God in his vocation, the more so as daddy Monipodio keeps such good order in that respect among all his children."</q></p>

			<p><q>"His must needs be a holy and edifying command," rejoined Rincon, "since it enjoins thieves to serve God."</q></p>

			<p><q>"It is so holy and edifying," exclaimed the stranger, "that I don't believe a better will ever be known in our trade. His orders are that we give something by way of alms out of all we steal, to buy oil for the lamp of a highly venerated image, well known in this city; and we have really seen great things result from that good work. Not many days ago, one of our cuatreros had to take three ansias for having come the Murcian over a couple of roznos, and although he was but a poor weak fellow, and ill of the fever to boot, he bore them all without singing out, as though they had been mere trifles. This we of the profession attribute to his particular devotion to the Virgin of the Lamp, for he was so weak, that, of his own strength, he could not have endured the first desconcierto of the hangman's wrist. But now, as I guess, you will want to know the meaning of certain words just used; I will take physic before I am sick--that is to say, give you the explanation before you ask for it.</q></p>

			<p><q>"Be pleased to know then, gentlemen, that a cuatrero is a stealer of cattle, the ansia is the question or torture.</q></p> 	
		</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>



