<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Rinconete y Cortadillo: Digital Edition</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>created by</resp>
					<name>Rebecca Beattie</name>				
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>University of Bologna</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Seville, Spain</pubPlace>
				<date>2022</date>
				<availability>
					<p>Digital Edition based on a print, critical edition, edited by Harry Sieber and published by Cátedra. This digital edition respects the rights outlined in this source, quoted here.</p>
					<p xml:lang="es">Reservados todos los derechos. El contenido de esta obra está protegido por la Ley, que establece penas de prisión y/o multas, además de las correspondientes indemnizaciones por daños y perjuicios, para quienes reprodujeren, plagiaren, distribuyeren o comunicaren públicamente, en todo o en parte, una obra literaria, artística o científica, o su transformación, interpretación o ejecución artística fijada en cualquier tipo de soporte o comunicada a través de cualquier medio, sin la preceptiva autorización</p>
					<p>The English text is freely and openly available from <ref target="http://www.online-literature.com/cervantes/exemplary-novels/2/">http://www.online-literature.com/cervantes/exemplary-novels/2/</ref></p>
					<p>Information regarding use of content from the Biblioteca Nacional de Espana can be found at <ref target="http://www.bne.es/es/Catalogos/BibliotecaDigitalHispanica/Pie/AvisoLegal/">http://www.bne.es/es/Catalogos/BibliotecaDigitalHispanica/Pie/AvisoLegal/</ref></p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl>
					<author>	
						<name>
							<surname>de Cervantes</surname>
							<forename>Miguel</forename>
						</name>
					</author>
					<editor>
						<name>
							<surname>de Robles</surname>
							<forename>Francisco</forename>
						</name>
					</editor>
					<title xml:lang="es">Novelas ejemplares</title>
					<publisher>Juan de la Cuesta</publisher>
					<pubPlace>Madrid, Spain</pubPlace>
					<date>1613</date>
				</bibl>
				<bibl>
					<author>	
						<name>
							<surname>de Cervantes</surname>
							<forename>Miguel</forename>
						</name>
					</author>
					<editor>
						<name>
							<surname>Sieber</surname>
							<forename>Harry</forename>
						</name>
					</editor>
					<title xml:lang="es">Novelas ejemplares I</title>
					<publisher>Ediciones Cátedra</publisher>
					<pubPlace>Madrid, Spain</pubPlace>
					<date>2009</date>
				</bibl>
				<bibl>
					<author>	
						<name>
							<surname>de Cervantes</surname>
							<forename>Miguel</forename>
						</name>
					</author>
					<editor>
						<name>
							<surname>Kelly</surname>
							<forename>Walter</forename>
						</name>
					</editor>
					<title xml:lang="es">Rinconete and Cortadillo. Or, Peter of the Corner and the Little Cutter</title>
					<publisher>The Literature Network</publisher>
					<date>1881</date>
				</bibl>	
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<normalization>
					<p>In the 1613 edition of the text, words, or partial words, at the end of a page are repeated, or partially repeated, at the start of the next page. The transription to go alongside the digitisation of the 1613 version standardises this practice by including the whole of the final word at the end of a page, and again at the start of the next page.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	
	<facsimile>
		<graphic url="FacsimileImages/73.jpg"/>
	</facsimile>
	
	<text>
		<body>
			<div xml:lang="es">
				<p>apariencia y los dos se quedaron esperando a la puerta. El salió luego y los llamó, y ellos entraron, y su guia les mandó esperar en un pequeño patio ladrillado, que de puro limpio y aljimifrado parecía que vertía carmín de lo mas fino. Al un lado estaba un banco de tres pies y al otro un cántaro desbocado, con un jarrillo encima no menos falto que el cántaro; a otra parte estaba una estera de enea, y en el medio, un tiesto, que en Sevilla llaman maceta, de albahaca.</p>

				<p>Miraban los mozos atentamente las alhajas de la casa en tanto que bajaba el señor Monipodio; y viendo que tardaba, se atrevió Rincón a entrar en una sala baja, de dos pequeñas que en el patio estaban, y vio en ella dos espadas de esgrima y dos broqueles de corcho, pendientes de cuatro clavos, y una arca grande, sin tapa ni cosa que la cubriese, y otras tres esteras de enea tendidas por el suelo. En la pared frontera estaba pegada a la pared una imágen de Nuestra Señora, destas de mala estampa, y más abajo pendía una esportilla de palma, y, encajada en la pared una almofía blanca, por do coligió Rincón que la esportilla servía de cepo para limosna, y la almofia, de tener agua bendita, y así era la verdad.</p>

				<p>Estando en esto entraron en la casa dos mozos de hasta veinte años cada uno, vestidos de estudiantes, y de allí a poco, dos de la esportilla y un ciego; y sin hablar palabra ninguno, se comenzaron a pasear por el patio. No tardó mucho, cuando entraron dos viejos de bayeta, con antojos, que los hacían graves y dignos de ser respectados, con sendos rosarios de sonadoras cuentas en las manos. Tras ellos entró una vieja halduda, y, sin decir nada se fue a la sala, y habiendo tomado agua bendita, con grandísima devoción, se puso de rodillas ante la imágen, y al cabo de una buena pieza, habiendo primero besado el suelo y levantados los brazos y los ojos al cielo otras tantas,</p>
			</div>
			
			<div xml:lang="en">
				<p>appearance. The two friends remained at the door to await their guide, who soon reappeared, and called to them to come in. He then bade them remain for the present in a little paved court, or patio, so clean and carefully rubbed that the red bricks shone as if covered with the finest vermilion. On one side of the court was a three-legged stool, before which stood a large pitcher with the lip broken off, and on the top of the pitcher was placed a small jug equally dilapidated. On the other side lay a rush mat, and in the middle was a fragment of crockery which did service as the recipient of some sweet basil.</p>

				<p>The two boys examined these moveables attentively while awaiting the descent of the Señor Monipodio, but finding that he delayed his appearance, Rincon ventured to put his head into one of two small rooms which opened on the court. There he saw two fencing foils, and two bucklers of cork hung upon four nails; there was also a great chest, but without a lid or anything to cover it, with three rush mats extended on the floor. On the wall in face of him was pasted a figure of Our Lady--one of the coarsest of prints--and beneath it was a small basket of straw, with a little vessel of white earthenware sunk into the wall. The basket Rincon took to be a poor box, for receiving alms, and the little basin he supposed to be a receptacle for holy water, as in truth they were.</p>

				<p>While the friends thus waited, there came into the court two young men of some twenty years each; they were clothed as students, and were followed soon afterwards by two of the basket boys or porters, and a blind man. Neither spoke a word to the other, but all began to walk up and down in the court. No long time elapsed before there also came in two old men clothed in black serge, and with spectacles on their noses, which gave them an air of much gravity, and made them look highly respectable: each held in his hand a rosary, the beads of which made a ringing sound. Behind these men came an old woman wearing a long and ample gown, who, without uttering a word, proceeded at once to the room wherein was the figure of Our Lady. She then took holy water with the greatest devotion, placed herself on her knees before the Virgin, and after remaining there a considerable time, first kissed the soil thrice, and then rising, lifted her arms and eyes towards heaven, in which attitude she remained a certain time longer.</p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>



