<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Rinconete y Cortadillo: Digital Edition</title>
				<author>Miguel de Cervantes</author>
				<editor>Harry Sieber</editor>
				<editor>Rebecca Beattie</editor>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>University of Bologna</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Seville, Spain</pubPlace>
				<date>2022</date>
				<availability>
					<p>Digital Edition based on a print, critical edition, edited by Harry Sieber and published by Cátedra. This digital edition respects the rights outlined in this source. The English text is freely and openly available from <ref target="http://www.online-literature.com/cervantes/exemplary-novels/2/">http://www.online-literature.com/cervantes/exemplary-novels/2/</ref></p>
					<p xml:lang="es">Reservados todos los derechos. El contenido de esta obra está protegido por la Ley, que establece penas de prisión y/o multas, además de las correspondientes indemnizaciones por daños y perjuicios, para quienes reprodujeren, plagiaren, distribuyeren o comunicaren públicamente, en todo o en parte, una obra literaria, artística o científica, o su transformación, interpretación o ejecución artística fijada en cualquier tipo de soporte o comunicada a través de cualquier medio, sin la preceptiva autorización</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl>
					<author>	
						<name>
							<surname>de Cervantes</surname>
							<forename>Miguel</forename>
						</name>
					</author>
					<editor>
						<name>
							<surname>Sieber</surname>
							<forename>Harry</forename>
						</name>
					</editor>
					<title xml:lang="es">Novelas ejemplares</title>
					<publisher>Ediciones Cátedra</publisher>
					<pubPlace>Madrid, Spain</pubPlace>
					<date>2009</date>
				</bibl>	
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<normalization>
					<p>In the 1613 edition of the text, words, or partial words, at the end of a page are repeated, or partially repeated, at the start of the next page. The transription to go alongside the digitisation of the 1613 version standardises this practice by including the whole of the final word at the end of a page, and again at the start of the next page.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	
	<facsimile>
		<graphic url="FacsimileImages/79.jpg"/>
	</facsimile>
	
	<text>
		<body>
			<div xml:lang="es">
				<p><q>hombres ¿Con aquél había yo de comer más pan a manteles, ni yacer en uno? Primero me vea yo comida de adivas estas carnes, que me ha parado de la manera que ahora veréis.</q></p>

				<p>Y alzándose al instante las faldas hasta la rodilla y aun un poco más, las descubrió llenas de cardenales:</p>

				<p><q>--Desta manera - prosiguió - me ha parado aquel ingrato del Repolido, debiéndome más que a la madre que le parió. Y ¿por qué pensáis que lo ha hecho? ¡Montas, que le di yo ocasión para ello! No, por cierto, no lo hizo más sino porque estando jugando y perdiendo, me envió a pedir con Cabrillas, su trainel, treinta reales, y no le envié mas de veinticuatro, que el trabajo y afán con que yo los había ganado ruego yo a los cielos que vayan en descuento de mis pecados. Y en pago desta cortesía y buena obra, creyendo él que yo le sisaba algo de la cuenta que él allá en su imaginación había hecho de lo que yo podría tener, esta mañana me sacó al campo, detrás de la güerta del Rey y allí, entre unos olivares me desnudó, y con la pretina, sin escusar ni recoger los hierros, que en malos grillos y hierros le vea yo, me dio tantos azotes, que me dejó por muerta. De la cual verdadera historia son buenos testigos estos cardenales que miráis.</q></p>

				<p>Aquí tornó a levantar las voces, aquí volvió a pedir justicia, y aquí se la prometió de nuevo Monipodio y todos los bravos que allí estaban.</p>

				<p>La Gananciosa tomó la mano a consolalla, diciéndole que ella diera de muy buena gana una de las mejores preseas que tenía, porque le hubiera pasado otro tanto con su querido.</p>

				<p><q>--Porque quiero - dijo - que sepas, hermana Cariharta, si no lo sabes, que a lo que se quiere bien se castiga: cuando estos bellacones nos dan, y azotan, y acocean, entonces nos adoran; si no, confiésame una verdad, por tu vida: después que te hubo Repolido castigado y brumado, ¿no te hizo alguna caricia?</q></p>

				<p><q>--¿Cómo una? - respondió</q></p>
			</div>
			
			<div xml:lang="en">
				<p><q>men! Will I ever eat again with him at the same table, or live under the same roof? Rather would I give this flesh of mine, which he has put into the state you shall see, to be devoured alive by raging beasts." So saying, she pulled up her petticoats to her knees, and even a little higher, and showed the wheals with which she was covered. "That's the way," she cried, "that I have been treated by that ungrateful Repolido, who owes more to me than to the mother that bore him.</q></p>

				<p><q>"And why do you suppose he has done this? Do you think I have given him any cause?--no, truly. His only reason for serving me so was, that being at play and losing his money, he sent Cabrillas, his scout, to me for thirty reals, and I could only send him twenty-four. May the pains and troubles with which I earned them be counted to me by heaven in remission of my sins! But in return for this civility and kindness, fancying that I had kept back part of what he chose to think I had got, the blackguard lured me out to the fields this morning, beyond the king's garden, and there, having stripped me among the olive trees, he took off his belt, not even removing the iron buckle--oh that I may see him clapped in irons and chains!--and with that he gave me such an unmerciful flogging, that he left me for dead; and that's a true story, as the marks you see bear witness."</q></p>

				<p>Here Cariharta once more set up her pipes and craved for justice, which was again promised to her by Monipodio and all the bravos present.</p>

				<p>The Gananciosa then tried her hand at consoling the victim; saying to her, among other things--<q>"I would freely give my best gown that my fancy man had done as much by me; for I would have you know, sister Cariharta, if you don't know it yet, that he who loves best thrashes best; and when these scoundrels whack us and kick us, it is then they most devoutly adore us. Tell me now, on our life, after having beaten and abused you, did not Repolido make much of you, and give you more than one caress?"</q></p>

				<p><q>"More than one!" replied</q></p>			
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>



