<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Rinconete y Cortadillo: Digital Edition</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>created by</resp>
					<name>Rebecca Beattie</name>				
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>University of Bologna</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Seville, Spain</pubPlace>
				<date>2022</date>
				<availability>
					<p>Digital Edition based on a print, critical edition, edited by Harry Sieber and published by Cátedra. This digital edition respects the rights outlined in this source, quoted here.</p>
					<p xml:lang="es">Reservados todos los derechos. El contenido de esta obra está protegido por la Ley, que establece penas de prisión y/o multas, además de las correspondientes indemnizaciones por daños y perjuicios, para quienes reprodujeren, plagiaren, distribuyeren o comunicaren públicamente, en todo o en parte, una obra literaria, artística o científica, o su transformación, interpretación o ejecución artística fijada en cualquier tipo de soporte o comunicada a través de cualquier medio, sin la preceptiva autorización</p>
					<p>The English text is freely and openly available from <ref target="http://www.online-literature.com/cervantes/exemplary-novels/2/">http://www.online-literature.com/cervantes/exemplary-novels/2/</ref></p>
					<p>Information regarding use of content from the Biblioteca Nacional de Espana can be found at <ref target="http://www.bne.es/es/Catalogos/BibliotecaDigitalHispanica/Pie/AvisoLegal/">http://www.bne.es/es/Catalogos/BibliotecaDigitalHispanica/Pie/AvisoLegal/</ref></p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl>
					<author>	
						<name>
							<surname>de Cervantes</surname>
							<forename>Miguel</forename>
						</name>
					</author>
					<editor>
						<name>
							<surname>de Robles</surname>
							<forename>Francisco</forename>
						</name>
					</editor>
					<title xml:lang="es">Novelas ejemplares</title>
					<publisher>Juan de la Cuesta</publisher>
					<pubPlace>Madrid, Spain</pubPlace>
					<date>1613</date>
				</bibl>
				<bibl>
					<author>	
						<name>
							<surname>de Cervantes</surname>
							<forename>Miguel</forename>
						</name>
					</author>
					<editor>
						<name>
							<surname>Sieber</surname>
							<forename>Harry</forename>
						</name>
					</editor>
					<title xml:lang="es">Novelas ejemplares I</title>
					<publisher>Ediciones Cátedra</publisher>
					<pubPlace>Madrid, Spain</pubPlace>
					<date>2009</date>
				</bibl>
				<bibl>
					<author>	
						<name>
							<surname>de Cervantes</surname>
							<forename>Miguel</forename>
						</name>
					</author>
					<editor>
						<name>
							<surname>Kelly</surname>
							<forename>Walter</forename>
						</name>
					</editor>
					<title xml:lang="es">Rinconete and Cortadillo. Or, Peter of the Corner and the Little Cutter</title>
					<publisher>The Literature Network</publisher>
					<date>1881</date>
				</bibl>	
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<normalization>
					<p>In the 1613 edition of the text, words, or partial words, at the end of a page are repeated, or partially repeated, at the start of the next page. The transription to go alongside the digitisation of the 1613 version standardises this practice by including the whole of the final word at the end of a page, and again at the start of the next page.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	
	<facsimile>
		<graphic url="FacsimileImages/81.jpg"/>
	</facsimile>
	
	<text>
		<body>
			<div xml:lang="es">
				<p><q>doce, aunque nunca se venda!</q></p>

				<p>A esto dijo Monipodio:</p>

				<p><q>--En mi presencia no ha de haber demasías: la Cariharta saldrá, no por amenazas, sino por amor mío, y todo se hará bien: que las riñas entre los que bien se quieren son causa de mayor gusto cuando se hacen las paces. ¡Ah, Juliana! ¡Ah niña! ¡Ah Cariharta mía! Sal acá fuera, por mi amor, que yo haré que el Repolido te pida perdón de rodillas.</q></p>

				<p><q>--Como él eso haga - dijo la Escalanta -, todas seremos en su favor y en rogar a Juliana salga acá fuera.</q></p>

				<p><q>--Si esto ha de ir por vía de rendimiento que güela a menoscabo de la persona - dijo el Repolido -, no me rendiré a un ejército formado de esguízaros; mas si es por vía de que la Cariharta gusta dello, no digo yo hincarme de rodillas, pero un clavo me hincaré por la frente en su servicio.</q></p>

				<p>Riyéronse desto Chiquiznaque y Maniferro, de lo cual se enojó tanto el Repolido, pensando que hacían burla dél, que dijo con muestras de infinita cólera:</p>

				<p><q>--Cualquiera que se riere o se pensase reír de lo que la Cariharta contra mí, o yo contra ella, hemos dicho o dijéremos, digo que miente y mentirá todas las veces que se riere o lo pensare, como ya he dicho.</q></p>

				<p>Miráronse Chiquiznaque y Maniferro de tan mal garbo y talle, que advirtió Monipodio que pararía en un gran mal si no lo remediaba; y así, poniéndose luego en medio dellos dijo:</p>

				<p><q>--No pase mas adelante, caballeros; cesen aquí palabras mayores, y desháganse entre los dientes; y pues las que se han dicho no llegan a la cintura, nadie las tome por sí.</q></p>

				<p><q>--Bien seguros estamos - respondió Chiquiznaque - que no se dijeron ni dirán semejantes monitorios por nosotros: qui si se hubiera imaginado que se decían en manos estaba el pandero que lo supieran bien tañer.</q></p>

				<p><q>--También tenemos acá pandero, sor Chiquiznaque - replicó el Repolido -, y también si fuere menester, sabremos tocar los cascabeles, y ya he dicho que el que se huelga, miente; y quien otra cosa pensare,</q></p>
			</div>
			
			<div xml:lang="en">
				<p><q>dozen though I make no charge for it."</q></p>

				<p>Here Monipodio interposed: <q>"In my presence," he said, "there shall be no violence. Cariharta will come out, not for your threats, but for my sake, and all will go well. Quarrels between people who love each other are but the cause of greater joy and pleasure when peace is once made. Listen to me, Juliana, my daughter; listen to me, my Cariharta. Come out to us, for the love of your friend Monipodio, and I will make Repolido beg your pardon on his knees."</q></p>

				<p><q>"Ah! if he will do that," exclaimed Escalanta, "we shall then be all on his side, and will entreat Juliana to come out."</q></p>

				<p><q>"If I am asked to beg pardon in a sense of submission that would dishonour my person," replied Repolido, "an army of lansquenets would not make me consent; but if it be merely in the way of doing pleasure to Cariharta, I do not say merely that I would go on my knees, but I would drive a nail into my forehead to do her service."</q></p>

				<p>At these words Chiquiznaque and Maniferro began to laugh, and Repolido, who thought they were making game of him, cried out in a transport of rage, <q>"Whoever shall laugh or think of laughing at anything whatsoever that may pass between Cariharta and myself, I say that he lies, and that he will have lied every time he shall laugh or think of laughing."</q></p>

				<p>Hearing this, Chiquiznaque and Maniferro looked at each other and scowled so sternly, that Monipodio saw things were likely to come to a crisis unless he prevented it. Throwing himself, therefore, into the midst of the group, he cried out, <q>"No more of this, gentlemen! have done with all big words; grind them up between your teeth; and since those that have been said do not reach to the belt, let no one here apply them to himself."</q></p>

				<p><q>"We are very sure," replied Chiquiznaque, "that such admonitions neither have been nor will be uttered for our benefit; otherwise, or if it should be imagined that they were addressed to us, the tambourine is in hands that would well know how to beat it."</q></p>

				<p><q>"We also, Sor Chiquiznaque, have our drum of Biscay," retorted Repolido, "and, in case of need, can make the bells as well as another. I have already said, that whoever jests in our matters is a liar: and whoever thinks otherwise,</q></p>			
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>



