<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Rinconete y Cortadillo: Digital Edition</title>
				<author>Miguel de Cervantes</author>
				<editor>Harry Sieber</editor>
				<editor>Rebecca Beattie</editor>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>University of Bologna</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Seville, Spain</pubPlace>
				<date>2022</date>
				<availability>
					<p>Digital Edition based on a print, critical edition, edited by Harry Sieber and published by Cátedra. This digital edition respects the rights outlined in this source. The English text is freely and openly available from <ref target="http://www.online-literature.com/cervantes/exemplary-novels/2/">http://www.online-literature.com/cervantes/exemplary-novels/2/</ref></p>
					<p xml:lang="es">Reservados todos los derechos. El contenido de esta obra está protegido por la Ley, que establece penas de prisión y/o multas, además de las correspondientes indemnizaciones por daños y perjuicios, para quienes reprodujeren, plagiaren, distribuyeren o comunicaren públicamente, en todo o en parte, una obra literaria, artística o científica, o su transformación, interpretación o ejecución artística fijada en cualquier tipo de soporte o comunicada a través de cualquier medio, sin la preceptiva autorización</p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl>
					<author>	
						<name>
							<surname>de Cervantes</surname>
							<forename>Miguel</forename>
						</name>
					</author>
					<editor>
						<name>
							<surname>Sieber</surname>
							<forename>Harry</forename>
						</name>
					</editor>
					<title xml:lang="es">Novelas ejemplares</title>
					<publisher>Ediciones Cátedra</publisher>
					<pubPlace>Madrid, Spain</pubPlace>
					<date>2009</date>
				</bibl>	
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<normalization>
					<p>In the 1613 edition of the text, words, or partial words, at the end of a page are repeated, or partially repeated, at the start of the next page. The transription to go alongside the digitisation of the 1613 version standardises this practice by including the whole of the final word at the end of a page, and again at the start of the next page.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	
	<facsimile>
		<graphic url="FacsimileImages/82a.jpg"/>
	</facsimile>
	
	<text>
		<body>
			<div xml:lang="es">
				<p><q><quote>Detente, enojado, no me azotes más,
				Que si bien lo miras, a tus carnes das.</quote></q></p>

				<p><q>Cántese a lo llano - dijo a esta sazón Repolido -, y no se toquen historias pasadas, que no hay para qué: lo pasado sea pasado, y tómese otra vereda, y basta.</q></p>

				<p>Tal le llevaban de no acabar tan presto el comenzado cántico, si no sintieran que llamaban a la puerta apriesa, y con ella salió Monipodio a ver quién era, y la centinela le dijo como al cabo de la calle habia asomado el alcalde de la justicia, y que delante dél venían el Tordillo y el Cernícalo, corchetes neutrales. Oyéronlo los de dentro, y alborotáronse todos de manera que la Cariharta y la Escalanta se calzaron sus chapines al revés, dejó la escoba la Gananciosa, Monipodio sus tejoletas, y quedó en turbado silencio toda la música; enmudeció Chiquiznaque, pasmóse el Repolido y suspendióse Maniferro, y todos, cuál por una y cuál por otra parte, desaparecieron, subiéndose a las azoteas y tejados para escaparse y pasar por ellos a otra calle. Nunca ha disparado arcabuz a deshora, ni trueno repentino espantó así a banda de descuidadas palomas como puso en alboroto y espanto a toda aquella recogida compañía y buena gente la nueva de la venida del alcalde de la justicia. Los dos novicios, Rinconete y Cortadillo, no sabían qué hacerse, estuviéronse quedos, esperando ver en qué paraba aquella repentina borrasca, que no paró en más de volver la centinela a decir que el alcalde se habia pasado de largo, sin dar muestra ni resabio de mala sospecha alguna.</p>

				<p>Y estando diciendo esto a Monipodio, llegó un caballero mozo a la puerta, vestido, como se suele decir, de barrio, Monipodio le entró consigo, y mandó llamar a Chiquiznaque, a Maniferro</p>
			</div>
			
			<div xml:lang="en">
				<p><q><quote>"Pause, angry lad! and do not beat me more,
				For 'tis thine own dear flesh that thou dost baste,
				If thou but well consider, and--"</quote></q></p>

				<p><q>"Fair and soft," exclaimed Repolido, at that moment, "give us no old stories, there's no good in that. Let bygones be bygones! Choose another gait, girl; we've had enough of that one."</q></p>

				<p>The canticle, for a moment interrupted by these words, was about to recommence, and would not, apparently, have soon come to an end, had not the performers been disturbed by violent knocks at the door. Monipodio hastened to see who was there, and found one of his sentinels, who informed him that at the end of the street was the alcalde of criminal justice, with the little Piebald and the Kestrel (two catchpolls, who were called neutral, since they did the community of robbers neither good nor harm), marching before him.</p>

				<p>The joyous company within heard the report of their scout, and were in a terrible fright. Escalanta and Cariharta put on their clogs in great haste, Gananciosa threw down her broom, and Monipodio his broken plate, every instrument sinking at once into silence. Chiquiznaque lost his joyous grin, and stood dumb as a fish; Repolido trembled with fear, and Maniferro looked pale with anxiety. But these various demonstrations were exhibited only for a moment,--in the next, all that goodly brotherhood had disappeared. Some rushed across a kind of terrace, and gained another court; others clambered over the roof, and so passed into a neighbouring alley. Never did the sound of a fowling piece, or a sudden peal of thunder, more effectually disperse a flock of careless pigeons, than did the news of the alcalde's arrival that select company assembled in the house of the Señor Monipodio. Rinconete and Cortadillo, not knowing whither to flee, stood in their places waiting to see what would be the end of that sudden storm, which finished simply enough by the return of the sentinel, who came to say that the alcalde had passed through the whole length of the street without seeming to have any troublesome suspicions respecting them, or even appearing to think of their house at all.</p>

				<p>While Monipodio was in the act of receiving this last report, there came to the door a gentleman in the prime of youth, and dressed in the half-rustic manner suitable to the morning, or to one residing in the country. Monipodio caused this person to enter the house with himself; he then sent to look for Chiquiznaque, Repolido, and Maniferro,</p>
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>



