<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="http://www.tei-c.org/release/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml"
	schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc>
			<titleStmt>
				<title>Rinconete y Cortadillo: Digital Edition</title>
				<respStmt>
					<resp>created by</resp>
					<name>Rebecca Beattie</name>				
				</respStmt>
			</titleStmt>
			<publicationStmt>
				<publisher>University of Bologna</publisher>
				<pubPlace>Seville, Spain</pubPlace>
				<date>2022</date>
				<availability>
					<p>Digital Edition based on a print, critical edition, edited by Harry Sieber and published by Cátedra. This digital edition respects the rights outlined in this source, quoted here.</p>
					<p xml:lang="es">Reservados todos los derechos. El contenido de esta obra está protegido por la Ley, que establece penas de prisión y/o multas, además de las correspondientes indemnizaciones por daños y perjuicios, para quienes reprodujeren, plagiaren, distribuyeren o comunicaren públicamente, en todo o en parte, una obra literaria, artística o científica, o su transformación, interpretación o ejecución artística fijada en cualquier tipo de soporte o comunicada a través de cualquier medio, sin la preceptiva autorización</p>
					<p>The English text is freely and openly available from <ref target="http://www.online-literature.com/cervantes/exemplary-novels/2/">http://www.online-literature.com/cervantes/exemplary-novels/2/</ref></p>
					<p>Information regarding use of content from the Biblioteca Nacional de Espana can be found at <ref target="http://www.bne.es/es/Catalogos/BibliotecaDigitalHispanica/Pie/AvisoLegal/">http://www.bne.es/es/Catalogos/BibliotecaDigitalHispanica/Pie/AvisoLegal/</ref></p>
				</availability>
			</publicationStmt>
			<sourceDesc>
				<bibl>
					<author>	
						<name>
							<surname>de Cervantes</surname>
							<forename>Miguel</forename>
						</name>
					</author>
					<editor>
						<name>
							<surname>de Robles</surname>
							<forename>Francisco</forename>
						</name>
					</editor>
					<title xml:lang="es">Novelas ejemplares</title>
					<publisher>Juan de la Cuesta</publisher>
					<pubPlace>Madrid, Spain</pubPlace>
					<date>1613</date>
				</bibl>
				<bibl>
					<author>	
						<name>
							<surname>de Cervantes</surname>
							<forename>Miguel</forename>
						</name>
					</author>
					<editor>
						<name>
							<surname>Sieber</surname>
							<forename>Harry</forename>
						</name>
					</editor>
					<title xml:lang="es">Novelas ejemplares I</title>
					<publisher>Ediciones Cátedra</publisher>
					<pubPlace>Madrid, Spain</pubPlace>
					<date>2009</date>
				</bibl>
				<bibl>
					<author>	
						<name>
							<surname>de Cervantes</surname>
							<forename>Miguel</forename>
						</name>
					</author>
					<editor>
						<name>
							<surname>Kelly</surname>
							<forename>Walter</forename>
						</name>
					</editor>
					<title xml:lang="es">Rinconete and Cortadillo. Or, Peter of the Corner and the Little Cutter</title>
					<publisher>The Literature Network</publisher>
					<date>1881</date>
				</bibl>	
			</sourceDesc>
		</fileDesc>
		<encodingDesc>
			<editorialDecl>
				<normalization>
					<p>In the 1613 edition of the text, words, or partial words, at the end of a page are repeated, or partially repeated, at the start of the next page. The transription to go alongside the digitisation of the 1613 version standardises this practice by including the whole of the final word at the end of a page, and again at the start of the next page.</p>
				</normalization>
			</editorialDecl>
		</encodingDesc>
	</teiHeader>
	
	<facsimile>
		<graphic url="FacsimileImages/83a.jpg"/>
	</facsimile>
	
	<text>
		<body>
			<div xml:lang="es">
				<p>puesta, diciéndole:</p>

				<p><q>--Voacé se detenga y cumpla su palabra, pues nosotros hemos cumplido la nuestra con mucha honra y con mucha ventaja: veinte ducados faltan, y no ha de salir de aquí voacé sin darlos, o prendas que lo valgan.</q></p>

				<p><q>--Pues ¿a esto llama vuesa merced cumplimiento de palabra - respondió el caballero -: dar la cuchillada al mozo habiéndose de dar al amo?</q></p>

				<p><q>--¡Qué bien está en la cuenta el señor! - dijo Chiquiznaque -. Bien parece que no se acuerda de aquel refrán que dice: «Quien bien quiere a Beltrán, bien quiere á su can.»</q></p>

				<p><q>--Pues ¿en qué modo puede venir aquí a propósito este refrán? - replicó el caballero.</q></p>

				<p><q>--¿Pues no es lo mismo - prosiguió Chiquiznaque - decir: «Quien mal quiere a Beltrán, mal quiere a su can»? Y así Beltrán es el mercader, voacé le quiere mal, su lacayo es su can, y dando al can se da a Beltrán, y la deuda queda líquida y trae aparejada ejecución: por eso no hay más sino pagar luego sin apercebimiento de remate.</q></p>

				<p><q>--Eso juro yo bien - añadió Monipodio -, y de la boca me quitaste, Chiquiznaque amigo, todo cuanto aquí has dicho; y así, voacé, señor galán, no se meta en puntillos con sus servidores y amigos, sino tome mi consejo y pague luego lo trabajado, y si fuere servido que se le dé otra al amo, de la cantidad que pueda llevar su rostro, haga cuenta que ya se la está curando.</q></p>

				<p><q>--Como eso sea - respondió el galán -, de muy entera voluntad y gana pagaré la una y la otra por entero.</q></p>

				<p><q>--No dude en esto - dijo Monipodio - más que en ser cristiano: que Chiquiznaque se la dará pintiparada, de manera que parezca que allí se le nació.</q></p>

				<p><q>--Pues con esa seguridad y promesa - respondió el caballero -, recíbase esta cadena en prendas de los veinte ducados atrasados y de cuarenta que ofrezco por la venidera cuchillada. Pesa mil reales, y podría ser que se quedase rematada, porque traigo entre ojos que serán menester otros catorce puntos antes de mucho.</q></p>

				<p>Quitóse</p>
			</div>
			
			<div xml:lang="en">
				<p>shoulders, saying: <q>"Be pleased to stop, Señor cavalier, and fulfil your promise, since we have kept our word with strict honour and to great advantage. Twenty ducats are still wanting to our bargain, and your worship shall not go from this place until you have paid them, or left us something of equal value in pledge."</q></p>

				<p><q>"Do you call this keeping your word," said the gentleman, "making a cut on the servant when you should have made it on the master?"</q></p>

				<p><q>"How well his worship understands the business," remarked Chiquiznaque. "One can easily see that he does not remember the proverb which says: 'He who loves Beltran, loves his dog likewise.'"</q></p>

				<p><q>"But what has this proverb to do with the matter?" inquired the gentleman.</q></p>

				<p><q>"Why, is it not the same thing as to say, 'He who loves Beltran ill, loves his dog ill too?' Now the master is Beltran, whom you love ill, and the servant is his dog; thus in giving the cut to the dog I have given it to Beltran, and our part of the agreement is fulfilled; the work has been properly done, and nothing remains but to pay for it on the spot and without further delay."</q></p>

				<p><q>"That is just what I am ready to swear to," cried Monipodio; "and you, friend Chiquiznaque, have taken all that you have said from my mouth; wherefore let not your worship, Señor gallant, be making difficulties out of trifles with your friends and servants. Take my advice and pay us what is our due. After that, if your worship would like to have another cut given to the master, of as many stitches as the space can contain, consider that they are already sewing up the wound."</q></p>

				<p><q>"If it be so," said the gentleman, "I will very willingly pay the whole sum."</q></p>

				<p><q>"Make no more doubt of it than of my being a good Christian, for Chiquiznaque will set the mark on his face so neatly, that he shall seem to have been born with it."</q></p>

				<p><q>"On this promise, then, and with this assurance," replied the gentleman, "receive this chain in pledge for the twenty ducats before agreed on, and for forty other ducats which I will give you for the cut that is to come. The chain weighs a thousand reals, and it may chance to remain with you altogether, as I have an idea that I shall want fourteen stitches more before long."</q></p>

				<p>Saying this, he took</p>			
			</div>
		</body>
	</text>
</TEI>



